<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Forms | The Starting Point]]></title>
  <link href="http://praveesh4.github.io/blog/categories/forms/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://praveesh4.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-16T22:39:39+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://praveesh4.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[praveesh4u@gmail.com]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Embedding related forms in Laravel 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://praveesh4.github.io/blog/2015/05/16/embedding-related-forms-in-laravel-5/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-16T20:43:52+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://praveesh4.github.io/blog/2015/05/16/embedding-related-forms-in-laravel-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes, there arises the need for embedding forms for creating more than one type of entities in a single form. Most of the time the two entities have a parent-child relation and to make things more complicated, dynamic addition and deletion of the child entity form will also be a part of the requirement. Symfony has functionality for implementing such forms built in within the framework which saves a lot of typing and time. Although Laravel 5&rsquo;s form implementation is relatively flexible compared to Symfony, there is no out of the box solution for embedding forms. After Googling for a decent amount of time and a Stackoverflow question that earned me a &ldquo;<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/help/badges/63/tumbleweed">Tumbleweed</a>&rdquo; badge, I decided to get my hands dirty. This may not be the most elegant solution but I can assure you that this works. I have tried to take advantage of cool laravel features like HTML macros so that the solution is more Laravel-ish.</p>

<p>The problem scenario in my case: I have a client entity which have one to many relation with a client user entity. That is, one client can have more than one client users. The form for adding a client should embed the form for adding the associated client users too. By default when the form loads, it should have form for adding one user. There should be a button for populating more client user forms in case a client has more than one form. Yeah, you guessed it right, we have to use Javascript.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/YRku4651uAsz5VDDCrWtEtIK16iEB1nmAMU-bzS3UsQo0Q90uUE-NDFKJ8LqJDZTRCdquQuuZV7sD6M=w1896-h875-rw" title="Final form" alt="This is how the final form should look like" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
